Hi, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is למד דלת, Lamed
Daled, 34. We're at the top. We are in the middle of
a long ברייתא braisa that is arguing how we know, or demonstrating
how we know, that שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus only relates to monetary
issues because the פסוקים psukim just say that he's an עד, eid,
והוא עד או ראה או ידע, vehu eid o ra'ah o yada,
but later in the end of ויקרא, Vayikra, there's another פרשה parsha
that's שבועת הפקדון, Shvuas Hapikadon, which talks about denying a פקדון, pikadon,
או בתשומת יד או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו, o bitshimus yad
o begazel o ashaq es amito, which is denying some monetary debt
or object owed to a friend, and there actually the קרבן korban
is an אשם, asham, but the ברייתא braisa here is making a
link to that פרשה parsha and saying the same way that's all
about monetary issues, שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus is all about monetary issues.
So we had different ways in which that link is made. Either
it's the times it says או, או, או, o, o, o, what
the גמרא Gemara calls אויין, o'in, so that links it. רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says that it says אחת מאלה, akhat me'eleh, which says
you make a distinction but doesn't say what that distinction is. רבי
יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili says והוא עד או ראה או ידע,
vehu eid o ra'ah o yada, a type of testimony that knowledge
or seeing is enough for even without sort of or seeing without
knowledge, knowledge without seeing, which he says only occurs in monetary matters.
We'll get back to that. And then finally now, we're dealing in
the middle of a long
דרשה drasha of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that also learns it from
שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon but makes this from a קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon is a broader scope, it applies to
men and to women, to those who can testify, those who can't
testify, all these different things, and even so it's limited to monetary
matters. So שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus which is a narrower scope should
also be limited to monetary matters. So in the middle of that
דרשה drasha we pick up on top of למד דלת עמוד א,
Lamed Daled amud alef, and he says like this.
So if that is, I'll just read from the second line: If
the case of שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon which is a broader scope
is אינו מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון eino medaber ela bitviat mamon is
only dealing when a demand is made for money, עדות שלא עשה
בו נשים כאנשים, edus shelo asa bo nashim k'anashim, שבועת העדות Shvuas
Ha'eidus which has a narrower scope that women are not treated like
men, it doesn't apply to women, קרובים כרחוקים, k'reivim kirchokim, relatives are
not treated like non-relatives, it doesn't apply to relatives, פסולים ככשרים, psulim
kich'sheirim, it doesn't treat people that are invalid to testify like those
who are, ואינו חייב אלא אחת לפני בית דין ve'eino chayav ela
akhat lifnei beis din and if the demand is made in the
presence of בית דין beis din you can't have multiple oaths because
after your first oath you can't testify anymore, so there the scope
is much narrower, אינו דין שלא יהא מדבר אלא בתביעת ממון? eino
din shelo yehei medaber ela bitviat mamon? So it makes a קל
וחומר. kal vachomer. Certainly that thing which has a narrower scope should
then also be limited to the case of monetary demands. So the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, or the ברייתא braisa says one minute:
מה לפקדון שכן לא עשה בו מושבע כנשבע. mah lapikadon sheken lo
asa bo mushba k'nishba. There's ways in which פקדון pikadon is narrower.
You can't assume that פקדון pikadon is always broader. Also you two
cases a way פקדון pikadon is narrower. Number one, פקדון pikadon we
don't say that imposing the שבועה shvuah is like making a שבועה
shvuah itself. Remember שבועת העדות, Shvuas Ha'eidus, the fundamental dynamic described in
the תורה Torah is ושמעה קול אלה, v'shomea kol alah, an oath
was imposed on you. We had another דרשה drasha that the person
had to be demanded directly. But anyway, that it was imposed on
you. By שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon we never learn that you can
have an oath imposed by somebody else. So there's ways that שבועת
הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon is narrower.
ומזיד כשוגג, u'mezid k'shogeg, also שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon only applies like
most קרבנות korbanos when it's בשוגג, b'shogeg, when it's not a willful
denial. But שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus we learn out it doesn't say
ונעלם, v'ne'elam, it applies even in a case of מזיד. mezid. So
since שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon has ways in which the scope is
narrower, you can't make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Just because it
only applies to monetary matters you can't say it certainly should be
true by שבועת העדות. Shvuas Ha'eidus. שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus is not
always narrower, there are ways in which שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus is
broader.
תאמר בעדות שכן עשה בו מושבע כנשבע. tomar b'edus sheken asa bo
mushba k'nishba. Here's ways in which עדות edus is broader. It applies
even if an oath is imposed and ומזיד כשוגג, u'mezid k'shogeg, and
applies even by a מזיד. mezid. So therefore you really can't learn
it out from a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. So תלמוד לומר תחטא
תחטא לגזירה שוה. talmud lomar techeta techeta l'gezeirah shavah. Fine. No קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, גזירה שוה. gezeirah shavah. Okay, it says both of
them it says תחטא. techeta. Okay, if a person sins, and what's
the פסוק? pasuk? The פסוק pasuk is תחטא. techeta.
So by שבועת העדות Shvuas Ha'eidus it says,
okay, one is 5:1 and one is 5:21.
So 5:1 is ונפש כי תחטא ושמעה קול אלה והוא עד או
ראה או ידע אם לוא יגיד ונשא עוונו, v'nefesh ki techeta v'shomea
kol alah vehu eid o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid v'nasa
avono, and the other one by שבועת הפקדון Shvuas Hapikadon is ונפש
כי תחטא ומעלה מעל בה' וכחש בעמיתו v'nefesh ki techeta u'ma'ala ma'al
b'Hashem v'kichash b'amito etc. So not just the word תחטא, techeta, ונפש
כי תחטא, v'nefesh ki techeta, it's like mamash opening with the same
phrase. So opposed to the link before which is based on a
word או, או, o, o, here's a link is based on the
word ונפש כי תחטא, v'nefesh ki techeta, another way to learn it
from
שבועת הפקדון. Shvuas Hapikadon.
So that's the ברייתא. braita. So now we are going to spend
most of the remainder of today's דף daf by analyzing and unpacking
this ברייתא. braita. Okay, and a little bit we'll get onto a
new topic. So let's take a look.
מתקיף לה רבה בר עולא. Matkif lah Rabba bar Ulla. So רבה
בר עולא Rabba bar Ulla ask, going back to the first דרשה,
drasha, the first דרשה drasha where it says או או או, o
o o, you know, you know, which it says ושמעה קול אלה
והוא עד או ראה או ידע, veshamah kol alah vehu ed o
raah o yada, right, and the other one it says או בתשומת
יד או בגזל או עשק את עמיתו, o bitshumat yad o begazel
o ashaq et amito, so the או’s o linked it. And it
says there says או’s o other places, it says yes, but both
of these או’s o are in cases where it is a שבועה,
shevuah, it is,
where was the link? It was a, it was a
שבועה, shevuah, there wasn't a כהן, kohen, and there was one other
which I'm not remembering. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara is going to
say there are other או’s o you could have linked it to.
מתקיף לה רבה בר עולא, Matkif lah Rabba bar Ulla, או או
ביטוי יוכיח. o o bitui yokhiach. What about the או’s o it
says by the שבועת ביטוי, shevuat bitui, right, להרע או להיטיב, lehara
o lehiteiv, although I don't, it doesn't say או o multiple times
there, anyway, but it says או’s o there by ביטוי, bitui, by
שבועת ביטוי, shevuat bitui, so let's learn it out from there. And
that's not limited to money. Remember that's just like a שבועה shevuah
that you're going to do something in the future. Okay.
או נפש, o nefesh, כי תשבע לבטא בשפתים להרע או להיטיב.
ki tishava levate bisfatayim lehara o lehiteiv. It's not the same או
או או o o o like a list of things. But okay,
okay, שהן אווין, shehen ovin, it's you've got the link of the
או’s, o ויש עמן שבועה, veyesh iman shevuah, there is a שבועה,
shevuah, ואין עמן כהן, ve-ein iman kohen, there is not a כהן,
kohen, that we threw in to exclude the case of a סוטה.
sotah. So you've got a שבועה, shevuah, no כהן, kohen, או’s, o
so that's what we did to link this to link עדות edut
to פקדון, pikadon, let's link עדות edut to ביטוי, bitui, which it's
not about money. ומדברין שלא בתביעת ממון, umedabrin shelo bitviat mamon, and
that's not limited to money. So how do you know to link
it to שבועת פקדון, shevuat pikadon, link it to שבועת ביטוי? shevuat
bitui? So the גמרא Gemara says no, מסתברא מפקדון הוה ליה למילף.
mistavra mipikadon hava leh lemeilaf. No, no, no, there's a greater link
to שבועת הפקדון, shevuat hapikadon, שכן תחטא מתחטא. sheken techeta mitecheta.
It's a little cheating, it's using the גזירה שווה gezeirah shavah that
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used at the end. Okay, these are linked
not just by the או’s o but also נפש כי תחטא, nefesh
ki techeta, which it says both by פקדון pikadon and עדות. edut.
So that's how you know to make the link. It's not just
the או’s o and you're not going to make the link to
שבועת ביטוי. shevuat bitui. Okay, אדרבה מביטוי
הוה ליה למילף, adraba mibitui hava leh lemeilaf, wait wait wait, no
no no, I'm going to argue in favor of linking it to
ביטוי, bitui, שכן חטאת מחטאת. sheken chatat michatat. Those, in fact the
חטאת chatat here does not mean like a word חטאת, chatat, it's
talking about the הלכה. halakhah. Okay, that actually the שבועת
עדות shevuat edut and שבועת ביטוי shevuat bitui are literally in the
same פרשה. parashah. They're in the exact same discussion and you bring
a קרבן עולה ויורד, korban oleh veyored, okay, so it's the same
type of a קרבן korban and they're literally in the same פרשה,
parashah, so let's more link it to שבועת ביטוי. shevuat bitui. Okay,
אלא מסתברא מפקדון הוה ליה למילף. ela mistavra mipikadon hava leh lemeilaf.
Fine. So now we've sort of got them even. You've got או’s
o on both sides of the equation, right here you've got
שבועת עדות, shevuat edut, here's שבועת עדות, shevuat edut, and here you
have ביטוי. bitui. These are all in one section here where it
says או, o, חטאת
עולה
ויורד, chatat oleh veyored,
and then a little bit later in the פרשה, parashah, very little
bit later, you have שבועת
פקדון
shevuat hapikadon and that's an אשם. asham. Okay, so the question is
which one to link this to? This, okay, this one here is
with money,
this one is without money. Which one do you link it to?
So both of them, so you've got the או’s, o okay, you
got the או’s, o both of them have the או’s, o okay,
you got the או’s, o alright, and you've got the other comparisons,
right, they're both שבועה, shevuah,
there's no כהן, kohen, okay, so which one is going to have
greater links? So in this you've got the argument that they're both
חטאת. chatat. Here that's one thing this has. This has נפש
כי
תחטא.
nefesh ki
techeta. Okay, so so far the sides are even. Alright, so which
which way is the link going to go? Alright, so let's take
a look.
So it says, אדרבה מביטוי הוה ליה למילף שכן חטאת מחטאת. adraba
mibitui hava leh lemeilaf sheken chatat michatat. אלא מסתברא מפקדון הוה ליה
למילף. ela mistavra mipikadon hava leh lemeilaf.
Here's why I'd rather learn it from פקדון, pikadon, שכן חטא במזיד
תביעה וכפירה ועברי sheken cheit bemeizid teviah vekhfirah ve-avrei (עברי? avrei?
I don't know how to even pronounce that word because רש"י Rashi
says it means עבר, avar, it's past oriented, ועבריה ve-avarya
I guess I don't know a weird word, ועברי, ve-avrei, ועברי).
ve-avrei Okay, ועברי. ve-avrei.
So here are the ways in which this is similar besides the
או’s o and the שבועה. shevuah. They both have the או’s o
and the שבועה, shevuah, so we've got to list other things other
than the או’s o and the שבועה shevuah that are going to
argue for the comparison. Number one is תחטא. techeta. Okay, שכן תחטא
sheken techeta
where were we? שכן חטא, Sheken Chet, which is means תחתיה. Teichta.
All right, what else? במזיד. Bemeizid. Okay, both of these, wait a
minute, did I skip a line? שכן חטא במזיד. Sheken Chet Bemeizid.
Both of these are במזיד Bemeizid like this says ונעלם Vene'elam שבועת
הפקדון. Shvuat Hapikadon.
Now that's interesting because we said a minute ago that it seemed
like שבועת הפקדון Shvuat Hapikadon did not apply במזיד. Bemeizid. All right,
we're going to get back to that idea but for now it's
so whether does שבועת הפקדון Shvuat Hapikadon apply במזיד. Bemeizid. Here we're
going to say it does, so they both have the idea במזיד.
Bemeizid. Why? Because this does not say ונעלם, Vene'elam, no ונעלם. Vene'elam.
Okay, so that's מזיד, Meizid, right, we said that before. Now let
me just draw a line here. All right, so we've got מזיד,
Meizid, what's the third one?
תביעה וכפירה. Tvia Ukfira.
Both of these, right, you're demanding something. Give me my object. Come
testify to me. Okay, I don't know, I'm sorry, I'm going out
of order here. תביעה
וכפירה. Tvia Ukfira. And both of these are test oriented.
Okay, do you know, I swear to me you don't know testimony,
swear to me I didn't give you my object. Four points of
comparison, that's why we're going to learn it out this way. Okay,
so then the גמרא Gemara says אדרבה Adaraba one minute,
מביתו הוי ליה למילף שכן חטא שירדה לחומש. Mibeito havei lei lemilaf
sheken chet sheyarda lechomesh. Okay, that's like a little mnemonic to remind
of it. The חטאת Chatat that went down to the fifth,
went down to the market.
Okay, what does that mean? Okay, so the points of comparison here
are number one it's a חטאת. Chatat. Number two it's a certain
type of a חטאת, Chatat, עולה ויורד. Oleh Veyored. That means שירדה,
Sheyarda, that it went down. And three, both of these there's no
חומש Chomesh in terms of the punishment. Okay, so this is like
the punishment aspects are similar, right, the punishment here is all the
same. It's a חטאת Chatat without a חומש. Chomesh. Here when you
swear falsely about a פקדון, Pikadon, not only do you bring an
אשם, Asham, you also bring a חומש. Chomesh. All right, so these
have similarities in terms of the circumstances of the event. Okay,
first of all they're described the same, they take place even במזיד
Bemeizid with a demand, they're test oriented. These, because they're in the
same פרשה, Parsha, have similarities in terms of the consequence. Okay, so
which way are you going to learn it out? So the גמרא
Gemara says הנך נפישין, Haneich Nefishin, nah we're going to learn it
out this way because there are more points of comparison. Four beats
out three. Okay, and therefore, because this is about money, this is
going to be about money as well. Okay, so that's how we
learn that out, that it's not a גזירה שוה. Gzeira Shava. If
it's just based on points of comparison, okay, they all have the
O's, but this has more points of comparison going that way. All
right, רבי עקיבא אומר. Rabbi Akiva Omer. Now we're going to do
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's דרשה. Drasha. That was looking at the O
דרשה. O Drasha. רבי עקיבא אומר והיה כי
יאשם לאחת מאלה,
Rabbi Akiva omer
vehaya ki ye'sham le'achat me'eileh, יש מאלה שהוא חייב ויש מאלה שהוא
פטור. Yeish me'eileh shehu chayav veyeish me'eileh shehu patur. Some of these
cases you're חייב, Chayav, some you're not. I'm going to draw the
line between when it's a שבועת העדות Shvuat Ha'edut about money and
not about money. So it's not really explicitly in the פסוק, Pasuk,
but the פסוק Pasuk does distinguish. So the גמרא Gemara says, where
were we? יש מאלה שהוא חייב ויש מאלה שהוא פטור. Yeish me'eileh
shehu chayav veyeish me'eileh shehu patur. הקיצר? Hakeitzad?
What's the line of distinction? This is still the ברייתא. Braita. תבעו
ממון חייב, תבעו דבר אחר פטור. Tva'o mamon chayav, tva'o davar acher
patur. If you're demanding money you're חייב, Chayav, if it's about something
else you're פטור. Patur. It's not explicit, but that's how I'll read
it. Okay, by the way, it's just a little bit confusing because
ד''א Daled Aleph which means דבר אחר, Davar Acher, right, that's often
when you see it abbreviated ד''א, Daled Aleph, it means here's a
different way of learning what we just said, or here's a different
argument to support the point I just made. Here דבר אחר, Davar
Acher, I mean, it means a different thing. If it's about money
it's this way, if it's something other than money, it doesn't apply.
Okay, now איפכא אנא. Ipcha Ana. All right, but what tells רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that's the line of division? Maybe I'll say the
opposite. Maybe only it's a שבועת העדות Shvuat Ha'edut when it's not
about money matters. Maybe money matters דווקא Davka you don't bring the
קרבן. Korban. So or maybe it's some other line of division. So
רבי עקיבא אהיי דרבי אליעזר סמיך. Rabbi Akiva ahei deRabbi Eliezer samich.
Okay, so wait, we misunderstood רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva says the גמרא Gemara was not coming to support the general
argument about how do we know that this is only about money.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was actually saying, oh by the way, you
guys are making a point that שבועת העדות Shvuat Ha'edut is all
about money, I want to point out something to you guys. The
fact that it says אחת מאלה Achat me'eileh to me tells me
there were actually certain types of money demands which you're not חייב
Chayav for. So actually the גמרא Gemara reads, it's not פשט Pshat
of the ברייתא. Braita. פשט Pshat of the ברייתא Braita is רבי
עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva's making another argument to show that we're talking about
money. But the גמרא's Gemara's reading it as he's pointing out, hey
you guys are all talking that it's only about money, it's all
about money, I want to point out that אחת מאלה Achat me'eileh
tells you not all cases of money. Okay, so which cases are
would you not be חייב Chayav for? מאי בינייהו? Mai beinaihu? So
what are they arguing about? בין רבי אליעזר בין רבי עקיבא. Bein
Rabbi Eliezer bein Rabbi Akiva. איכא בינייהו משביע עדי קרקע. Ika beinaihu
mashbia edei karka. Okay,
this is what we mentioned before. There's a normal principle that you
don't take an oath about land. If Michael and I are debating
and let's say he's a
מודה במקצת. Modeh bemiktzat. whatever, one parcel. We wouldn't say take a
שבועת מודה במקצת. shevuat modeh bimiktzat. Sometimes we even make it even
in cases that are not even directly about land there's a discussion.
Let's say I say Michael, you damaged, you know, whatever, you owe
me a money that was lent with a שטר shtar and therefore
there was a שיעבוד shibud or lean on the land, you know,
you owe me a hundred dollars and he says I only owe
you fifty dollars. So even though we're only arguing, it's still, according
to certain opinions, he wouldn't make a שבועת מודה במקצת shevuat modeh
bimiktzat because even though we're arguing a hundred versus fifty, since the
hundred versus fifty has implications for leans on land, there wouldn't be
a שבועה shevua that would even relate to a lean on land.
Okay, so that's the general principle. But here it's a little different.
Because here, when I'm paying the witnesses to come and testify for
me, yes, I'm trying to extract land there from חנן Hanan who's
sitting on my property without a right, okay, but on the other
hand, their שבועה shevua isn't about whether they owe me land or
not, their שבועה shevua is about whether they know testimony or not,
right? So does this fall into the category that you don't take
a שבועה shevua about land? It's an interesting question. So since that's
a question that's worth asking, the גמרא Gemara says maybe that's the
debate that's going on here. Maybe when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
you don't have a שבועה shevua in certain cases of money, maybe
what he means is when it's a שבועה shevua relating to land,
okay, of testimony about land. So the גמרא Gemara says בין רבי
אליעזר לבין רבי עקיבא איכא בינייהו משביע עדי קרקע. bein Rabbi Eliezer
levein Rabbi Akiva ika beinaihu mashbia edei karka.
If you're having people take, if you're taking them to take an
oath about testimony relating to land. רבי אליעזר חייבין, Rabbi Eliezer chayavin,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer doesn't make distinctions, he would say you're חייב.
chayav. רבי עקיבא פטור, Rabbi Akiva patur, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
you're not חייב chayav in all cases, meaning you wouldn't be חייב
chayav in this case. So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
ורבי יוחנן דאמר התם משביע עדי קרקע אפילו רבי אליעזר פטור הכא
מאי איכא בין רבי אליעזר לרבי עקיבא. veRabbi Yochanan de'amar hatam mashbia
edei karka afilu Rabbi Eliezer patur hacha mai ika bein Rabbi Eliezer
leRabbi Akiva. Later in a different discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to say that even רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer of our ברייתא Baraita who says you're חייב chayav for monetary
matters would not say all monetary matters. He says that everybody would
agree you're not חייב chayav for עדות eidus relating to land. Okay,
so according to that, everybody agrees that it doesn't apply to land.
So what would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
be debating about? איכא בינייהו עדי קנס. ika beinaihu edei knas. Ah,
what we discussed the other day, the משנה Mishnah yesterday, the פשט
pshat of that משנה Mishnah said witnesses about a קנס knas are
חייב. chayav. Okay, but maybe that's what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says
not like that. Maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says not all monetary
matters, monetary matters that are קנס, knas, maybe you would be exempt
from. Why? Doesn't say. Is this based on the issue we raised
yesterday? Because of, remember the issue we raised yesterday is that maybe
since the guy could come and admit to it, so even when
I cause the witnesses to swear, it's not their testimony alone that's
going to make me win or it's not necessarily that their testimony
will make me win, he could always beat them to court and
admit it and then get out of it, right? That was what
we said yesterday. So therefore and the גמרא Gemara raised that question,
you know. פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah is that you're חייב
chayav by עדי קנס. edei knas. So maybe that's what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer is, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is disagreeing with. Okay, that
was understanding רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, not all cases of money, maybe
the case he would exclude is witnesses about a קנס. knas. Now
we move on to רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili. רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer. רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili
was the interesting one, he was talking about not just technical points
of comparison, but about the nature of the testimony. Okay, רבי יוסי
הגלילי אומר והוא עד או ראה או ידע. Rabbi Yose HaGlili omer
vehu ed o ra'ah o yada. It says by this שבועת העדות,
shvuas haeidus, he was an עד eid or he saw or he
knew. So what do we learn from that? He says from this
I'm going to learn it's money, because it's talking about a type
of a testimony that could be seen without knowing and knowing without
seeing. Okay, או ידע בעדות המתקיימת בראייה בלא ידיעה ובידיעה בלא ראייה
הכתוב מדבר. o yada be'eidus hamiskayemes bire'iyah belo yedia biyedia belo re'iyah
haksav medaber. The type of testimony that could work with knowing without
seeing and seeing without knowing. Okay, and that would not apply by
a capital crime or by מלקות malkus or anything else where you
clearly have to see. I mean you can't just know because you
have inferred it, right, or know it indirectly, you have to see
directly and you have to know what you're seeing. The גמרא Gemara
will explore exactly this.
But אמר ליה רב פפא לאביי, amar leh Rav Pappa leAbaye,
now whereas I should just say before the גמרא Gemara is now
going to quote, what is the case of monetary matters where knowing
is enough or seeing without knowing is enough? So knowing was enough
is that the witnesses say we heard Michael admit to you דב
Dov that he owes you a hundred dollars. So they don't know
he borrowed a hundred dollars, they didn't see, excuse me, him borrow
a hundred dollars, but they know based on his admission that he
owes it to me. That's knowing without seeing. What's seeing without knowing?
Seeing without knowing is actually the bigger חידוש. chiddush. Seeing without knowing
is, by the way, the reason that doesn't work in other cases
is because self-admission only is meaningful in monetary matters. In other manners,
you can't incriminate yourself. The Fifth Amendment says that you are not
required to incriminate yourself, right, whereas הלכה halacha says it doesn't work
even if you try to incriminate yourself, you know, in matters that
are not monetary matters. So therefore the idea of admission, which is
knowing without seeing, only works in monetary matters. What's the case of
seeing without knowing? The case of seeing without knowing is I say,
you know, חנן Chanan and דוד David come testify to me you
saw me count out a hundred dollars to Michael. Okay, now, of
course the point is, what good is that going to do me?
Maybe it was a gift, maybe I was paying him back a
loan, not lending him the money, right? So that's not clear why
that works in monetary matters. The way רש"י Rashi explains it, it
works in the sense that when you come, that might pressure Michael
to admit. Of course that sounds like a גוביי ממונא goveir mammon
type of a thing. The גמרא Gemara is going to deal with
a case where maybe I say, Michael, I counted out a hundred
dollars to you yesterday and I lent it to you, and Michael
denies that the event ever took place. And in that context, maybe
them testifying that I counted it out, right, now maybe it's too
late for him to claim that it meant something else, although that's
not exactly clear. So, actually, that case of seeing without knowing, it's
not black, it's not so clear why what scenario that works in
monetary matters, but the גמרא Gemara is going to take it for
granted that it does not work in cases like capital crimes. Okay,
so let's take a look. Now we're going to look at this.
Okay, אמרי רב פפא לאביי, amrei Rav Pappa le-Abaye, רב פפא Rav
Pappa said to אביי. Abaye. Oh, so, לימא רבי יוסי הגלילי לית
ליה דרב אחא. leima Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili leit lei de-Rav Acha.
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili who says that testimony of knowing
without seeing doesn't work, only works in monetary matters, not in other
things like capital crimes. Does that mean he disagrees with רב אחא?
Rav Acha? What's the רב אחא? Rav Acha? דתניא, De-tanya, we turn
a ברייתא. Braisa. אמר רבי אחא אומר, Amar Rabbi Acha Omer, גמל
האוחר בין הגמלים, gamal ha-ocheir bein ha-gemalim,
if a camel was like rooting, you know, like a goring amongst
the other camels or one explanation רש"י Rashi has is that he
was actually fornicating, okay, and anyway, ונמצא גמל הרוג בצידו. ve-nimtza gamal
harug be-tzido. And then you found a dead camel near it. So
you saw this camel like, you know, you didn't actually see him
kick this other camel, but you saw him acting wild, and you
went into the herd and you saw a dead camel right next
to him, okay, ונמצא גמל הרוג בצידו, ve-nimtza gamal harug be-tzido, בידוע
שזה הרגו, be-yaduah she-zeh harago, okay,
you know that this camel killed the other one and therefore you
can collect from the other. So how would you, what's that a
case of? ידיעה Yediah without ראייה. re-iyah. All right. So look, you
see ידיעה yediah without ראייה re-iyah works. Okay, and so do we,
are we going to say רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili disagrees
with that?
דאיתי דרב אחא, di-itay de-Rav Acha, because if you hold of רב
אחא, Rav Acha, that that's considered knowledge, so בדיני נפשות נמי משכחת
לה. be-dinei nefashot nami mishkachas lah. I can give you a similar
case of knowledge like that in a in a case of a
capital crime. You just replace the camels with people. Okay, דרבי שמעון
בן שטח, d'Rebbi Shimon ben Shetach, like the story of רבי שמעון
בן שטח. Rebbi Shimon ben Shetach. דתניא, De-tanya, we turn a ברייתא.
Braisa. אמר רבי שמעון בן
שטח, Amar Rebbi Shimon ben Shetach, אראה בנחמה, ereh be-nechamah,
I will see in the consolation of Jerusalem. It's like a way
of taking an oath.
But this is things just the opposite. No, I mean may I
not see, you're right.
It's sort of implicit, may I not see in the consolation if
this is not true. אם לא ראיתי אחד שרץ אחר חבירו לחורבה,
im lo ra'iti echad she-ratz achar chaveiro le-churvah, I once saw this
guy running after somebody else into this like desolate area, this area
where you know of like where there was like you know these
destroyed buildings. ורצתי אחריו, ve-ratzti acharo,
and I ran after to see what was going on, okay, or
maybe to try to intervene. ומצאתי סייף בידו, u-matzati sayif be-yado, and
when I caught up to the guy, the guy who was pursuing,
there he was, he was holding a סייף, sayif, a knife in
his hand,
ודם מנטף, ve-dam mitatef, and blood was dripping from it, והרוג מפרפר,
ve-harug mefarpeir, and on the ground was a guy with knife wounds
thrashing around, dead, who was dying. אמרתי לו, amarti lo, I said
to the guy with the knife, רשע, rasha, wicked person, מי הרגו
לזה, mi harago la-zeh, who else, there's nobody here for a thousand
miles, who else could have killed this guy? או אני או אתה,
o ani o atah, it's either me or you, and I know
it's not me. אבל מה אעשה, aval mah e'eseh, what can I
do to you? שאין דמך מסור בידי, she-ein damcha masur be-yadi,
I don't have the right to to take your to take your
life. שהרי אמרה תורה על פי שנים עדים או שלשה עדים יומת
המת. she-harei amrah torah al pi shenayim eidim o sheloshah eidim yumos
ha-meis. You need two witnesses. אלא המקום יפרע ממך, ela Ha-Makom yifra
mimcha,
God should take should should give pay you back. אמרו לא זז
משם עד שנשכו נחש ומת. amru lo zaz mi-sham ad she-nashkho nachash
u-meis. And before they left, a snake came out and bit the
guy the murderer and he died. Now, now, so you see, if
you can if you can assume the camel killed the camel, you
should be able to assume here the only problem was he said
it was one witness. Had there been two witnesses it sounds like
it would have worked. So presumably so there are cases in capital
crimes where you can judge it based on, you know, knowledge without
seeing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says where were we? אלא לא
אמרו לו, ela lo amru lo, okay.
אפילו תימא איתי דרב אחא, afillu teima itay de-Rav Acha, no, he
could hold of רב אחא. Rav Acha. בשלמא ידיעה בלא ראייה משכחת
לה, be-shlama yediah be-lo re-iyah mishkahas lah, it's true, by capital crimes
you could also have a case of seeing of knowing without seeing.
אלא ראייה בלא ידיעה היכי משכחת לה, ela re-iyah be-lo yediah heichi
mishkahas lah, you won't have a case of seeing without knowing. We'll
get to that in a minute but before we move on we
have to pause here because the גמרא Gemara is saying something crazy,
right? Because this really doesn't make any sense. First of all
it goes against everything we know, everything we... Pointing out is that
exactly that case described by רבי שמעון בן שטח Rabbi Shimon ben
Shatach would not be accepted even if you had two witnesses. First
of all, parenthetically, תוספות Tosafot points out where was the התראה, hatra'ah,
where was the warning? So תוס Tos says maybe the murderer was
a חבר chaver and maybe we're assuming a חבר chaver like a
תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham who doesn't need התראה. hatra'ah. But okay, that's
like a side point, but it's still problematic. Besides which, you know,
the constant message throughout ש״ס Shas is if you want to get
somebody for murder or for מלקות, malkus, you need direct witnessing of
it. You cannot draw any inferences. If you didn't see it, I'm
sorry, you could know a hundred percent. That's point number one. And
the גמרא Gemara here seems to concede the point that that would
work. It actually sounds that way from שמעון בן שטח, Shimon ben
Shatach, but that's not normally the position that we take. Number two.
Right. Yes. Number two is that what are you asking about רבי
אחא? Rabbi Acha? You should have asked about רבי שמעון בן שטח.
Rabbi Shimon ben Shatach. רבי אחא Rabbi Acha just said it about
a camel. It's very nice that a camel kills another camel, but
let me tell you even with all the animal activists out there,
that's not murder, okay? I mean, it's the death of a camel,
okay? But it is not halachically an act, it is a case
of דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. If I want to collect from you
for your camel killing mine, that's a monetary case. So even if
רבי אחא Rabbi Acha allows for that case to be processed, what
does that say about applying that to capital cases? It's very bizarre.
It's almost like the גמרא Gemara says that רבי אחא's Rabbi Acha
primary חידוש chiddush is that you can say that you know for
sure. And once you know for sure in that case, why not
apply it to capital? But it's very strange, and תוספות Tosafot sort
of asks this question, that the גמרא Gemara seems to concede the
point that this would work in a capital case because it doesn't
work in a capital case. And even רבי אחא Rabbi Acha who
says his case, says it by a monetary issue, he does not
say it by capital.
והוא הדין לדין דיני
נפשות?
Ve-hu ha-din le-din
dinei nefashot?
I know, תוספות Tosafot asks that question.
Okay, so maybe that's why he was killed by השם. Hashem.
Right, well that's clearly. But the funny thing also is that רבי
שמעון בן שטח Rabbi Shimon ben Shatach mentions that he was only
one witness. It sounded like if there was two... I don't know,
okay. Sometimes might be you gotta live with the question, alright? But
it's a big... I know, you can look at תוספות. Tosafot. It's
a strange גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara almost seems to be saying
even in theory were I to concede this point, I'm going to
still make this other difference between ממונות mamonot and נפשות nefashot about
seeing without knowing. Okay, maybe in theory I'll concede the point of
knowing without seeing, but all I'm pointing out is don't allow the
theoretical sort of concession of the גמרא Gemara to mislead you. The
הלכה Halacha is that this absolutely does not work by דיני נפשות
dinei nefashot and even רבי אחא's Rabbi Acha case was not a
case... was a ממונות mamonot case, not a נפשות nefashot case.
Yes, Gemara says...
ראיה... re'iyah... ידיעה... yedi'ah...
Okay, so yes, that is a good point. Nacho...
oh not... sorry... Jacob, sorry, what's happening in my head today. Jacob
reminds us that there is a case where
there
are a small number of cases in דיני נפשות dinei nefashot where
we don't have to see something explicitly, but that's a case where
we can sort of almost fill in the blanks, not of something
we didn't see, but to interpret what we are seeing. So the
case that Jacob is referring to is the discussion in the גמרא,
Gemara, what type of testimony do you need, actually but this is
a good point about how much you do have to you know
the you know the generally assume you have to see things directly.
What do you have to see to to make somebody like you
know to find guilt or whatever, to be able to testify against
somebody in a case of a forbidden act of intercourse? Okay, do
you actually have to see, you know, you know the you know
the genitals or whatever? So you know, in the act. And the
the way we פוסקן pasken is, it's enough to see them under
the covers and acting as and going through and doing the exact
motions that they would be doing if they were actually having intercourse.
And then you can infer that that's what's happening even if you
didn't directly see the genitals. Okay, so you're right, that's somewhat similar,
but the difference in that case is you are seeing them doing
something and you are just a little bit filling in the the
blanks of the little bit that you're not seeing, right? So if
you imagine this case of רבי שמעון בן שטח, Rabbi Shimon ben
Shatach, right, let's say that and first of all it might be
that that's like, but anyway, you know, that that case is, you
know, under ninety-nine point nine nine percent of the cases you don't
have the access to see that, so that's a case we sort
of allow that to be assumed. But let's imagine a case like
this for רבי שמעון בן שטח. Rabbi Shimon ben Shatach. You were
looking through the window and you saw the guy going like this
and you saw every time he picked up there was more blood
on his knife, okay? But you didn't actually see the body below.
And then you walked in and you saw the body below, right?
So that would be something comparable. That's already different. Maybe that case
we would connect the dots, okay? But yes, there are cases where
we will connect the dots and fill in the blanks, especially if
it's to just not say something you didn't see at all, but
to explain what you are seeing. Okay, but the general rule is
you have to see directly.
Did we need witnesses with the adultery also? Did they need warning?
Yes, yes, so they had to see.
Okay, so.
Okay, but the general rule is you have to see directly. So
it's strange that the גמרא Gemara seems to be conceding maybe you
don't have to see directly, but let's go on to the other
point. Okay, so just bracket that theoretical concession because that is not
the הלכה. halakha. Okay, but that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying
right now. Even if I'd grant theoretically that you don't have to
see directly by דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, there's this other point that
they're not similar, that there is a difference. What's this other point
that there is a difference? So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא bishlama
ידיעה yedia בלא belo ראייה reia משכחת meshkachat לה, la, fine. Maybe
you can have a case in דיני נפשות dinei nefashot of knowing
without seeing. אלא ella ראייה בלא ידיעה re'ia belo yedia. היכי heichi
משכחת meshkachat לה? la? You can't have a case of seeing without
knowing. Okay, now how does that work by דיני ממונות dinei mamonot
itself? It's not so clear. We discussed that before. Come testify that
you saw me give him a hundred dollars. What good is that
going to do me? But let's talk for a moment about why
that doesn't work by דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. Okay, מי mi לא
lo so the גמרא Gemara says אלא ella
ראייה reia בלא belo ידיעה yedia היכי heichi משכחת meshkachat לה? la?
מי לא בעי מידע mi lo ba'ei meida, there's things, facts that
you have to
know אם im עובד oved כוכבים kochavim הרג harag או o ישראל
Yisrael הרג. harag.
Murdering a non-Jew is not punishable by the death penalty. Murdering a
Jew is. Somebody says that he killed somebody, you're going to have
to tell me if you want to be able to prosecute, I
need to know the relevant facts. Okay, and if the עדים edim
don't know the relevant facts, okay. Now, of course, the interesting thing
is maybe they don't have to testify. What if we went over
afterwards and we got an idea of the victim not through the
עדים? edim? Okay, now, you know, so it's not exactly clear that
that has to be folded into the עדות edut just because we
need other relevant facts. Okay, but anyway, so you have to know
if he was a Jew or a non-Jew. אם im אדם adam
טרפה treifa הרג harag או o שלם shalem הרג. harag. Was it
a person that was full or was it a person with some
type of internal injury which would mean that the murderer then would
be technically exempt from the execution? Okay, now, תוספות Tosafot actually says,
what are you talking about? We can just assume that he was
a healthy person. Okay, which is actually an interesting question which was
asked the other day, right? Sometimes you are allowed to fold in
assumptions into what you're seeing. All right, so you're allowed to assume
that the victim was a maybe you can't assume he's a Jew
or non-Jew if you're living in a in a community that's a
let's say, you know, that that has you know, that that's a
mixed community. But if you're living in your tiny little שטעטל, shtetl,
okay, that no non-Jews almost never come in, you don't have to
have explicit testimony that he's a Jew, you can just assume that.
You can assume that he's a healthy person and not a person
who's a טרפה. treifa. So תוספות Tosafot actually says that actually you
would only need to clarify when there was a basis for doubt.
If we don't even though you told us you saw A kill
B, there's reasons that we cannot assume, would not take for granted
certain things. We have reasons to think he might be a guy
that was a טרפה. treifa. You killed him in the hospital. Okay,
we have reasons to think he might be a non-Jew. We have
reasons to think whatever. In those types of cases, we would have
to have that know that explicitly before we could go forward. Now,
that's similar to the case of me counting out money to Michael,
because right off the bat, we have no idea how to interpret
that. It's clear we need more information. Okay, so therefore, says that
at least doesn't work by דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. Of course, the
irony is it doesn't work by itself, but it doesn't mean it
has to be a part of my עדות. edut. Maybe we could
get that information elsewhere. All right, so again, if anything, this is
a weaker point of distinction than the other point. But it's saying
here at least is where דיני ממונות dinei mamonot is different than
דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot. דיני ממונות dinei mamonot somehow can help to
bring your testimony to court to say that you saw this guy
count out money for this other guy, that'll help this person in
court, even if you don't know what that was about, it'll help
back up his claim. Whereas by דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, an incomplete
testimony, seeing certain actions without knowing relevant facts is not going to
win is not going to do the work in court. It's not
going to be sufficient. Yes.
So, flipping that, one of the ways that some פוסקים poskim have
allowed כהנים kohanim to go to medical school is that they you
can assume that all the dead bodies are not Jews.
Right. Well, that's in that case. Yes, correct. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: שמע
מינה shema mina. should we infer from this דקסבר dekasavar רבי Rabbi
יוסי Yossi הגלילי HaGlili משביע mashbia עד ed קנס knas פטור? patur?
Now, maybe
we should what's the relevance of this idea about that he says
it works knowledge without seeing, seeing without knowledge? Should I therefore infer
from this that when it comes to witnesses about an aspect of
a קנס knas you should be exempt? Why? Because a קנס knas
is like a type of a punishment and therefore if you what's
the example of knowing without seeing? Remember we had an example of
knowing without seeing when the guy admitted. But if Michael admitted to
a קנס, knas, you can't testify about that, that's not that doesn't
obligate him. So since רבי Rabbi יוסי Yossi הגלילי HaGlili requires it
to be a case of knowing without seeing, seeing without knowing, that
would seem to exclude the case of a קנס. knas. שמע מינה
shema mina should we infer from this דקסבר dekasavar רבי Rabbi יוסי
Yossi הגלילי HaGlili משביע mashbia עד ed קנס knas פטור? patur? דאי
dei סלקא salka דעתך daatach חייב, chayav, נהי nehi דידיעה deyedia בלא
belo ראייה reia אשכחן ashkechan לה, la, we can have a case
of ידיעה yedia without ראייה. reia We saw You know, Michael's ox
goring my slave or something like that. I mean I don't know
what that case would be without ידיעה. yedia Anyway, we could see,
have seen the action but missing some critical pieces of information. Okay,
that might work.
Wait, isn't that the action? That's ראייה reia. בלא belo ידיעה. yedia.
היא ידיעה בלא ראייה. Hi yedia belo re'ia.
Oh,
I'm sorry. You're right. I got it wrong. נהי ידיעה בלא ראייה
אשכחן לה. nehi yedia belo re'ia ashkechan lah.
One minute. How do you have ידיעה yedia without ראייה? re'ia? ידיעה
yedia without ראייה re'ia is where he admits. But that doesn't work
by קנס. knas. Let me just check Rashi. That's what
we just had a second
before about the שומר שכר shomer sachar case, right?
Yeah.
Oh, I guess that's a good point. You're right. You're right. If
we're assuming ידיעה yedia without ראייה re'ia works even in a capital
case, it would work even in a case so it's not because
he admitted, it's because we saw, you know, we saw something and
we didn't see anything and we drew certain conclusions. Yes, thank you,
Michael. Okay, ואי סלקא דעתך דחייב נהי דידיעה בלא ראייה אשכחן לה.
ve'ei salka da'atcha de'chayav nehi diyedia belo re'ia ashkechan lah. You've we've
already conceded the fact that maybe not direct seeing could work and
maybe that could even work in a capital case, so could work
in a case of קנס knas as well, okay, cause you just
make certain inferences. So ראייה בלא ידיעה מי לא בעי מידע? re'ia
belo yedia mi lo ba'ei meida? But one minute, how about the
case of seeing without knowing? Seeing without knowing isn't going to be
sufficient if they're missing critical pieces of information. Okay, so what what
would be the example? So מי mi לא lo בעי bei מידע,
meida you have to know, נכרית בעל או בת ישראל בעל, nochris
ba'al o bas Yisrael ba'al, if it were the case for example
of a case of rape or seduction where there is the קנס.
knas. Okay, you have to know if the woman he raped or
seduced was a Jewish woman or non-Jewish woman. בתולה בעל או בעולה
בעל, besula ba'al o be'ula ba'al, was she a virgin or was
she a non-virgin? Okay, so therefore, just like we've discussed before by
murder, seeing is not enough without the relevant facts. By קנס knas
as well seeing won't be enough without a relevant fact. So should
that exclude קנס knas as well? So יתיב רב המנונא. yativ Rav
Hamnuna. So I'm sorry, I
actually I read that as a question but actually that was a
statement. Okay, sorry about that guys. All right, so שמע shma מינה.
mina Let's read that one more time. שמע shma מינה mina just
read it without the question mark. From what we've just said, we
can infer that קסבר רבי יוסי הגלילי משביע קנס פטור. kasavar Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili mashbi'a knas patur. That you're exempt, קנס knas is also
exempt. דאי סלקא דעתך דחייב נהי דידיעה בלא ראייה אשכחן לה, de'ei
salka da'atcha de'chayav nehi diyedia belo re'ia ashkechan lah, we could have
a case of knowing without seeing because we made certain inferences and
we're saying that that's going to be okay. It would be okay
even by a capital case. But ראייה בלא ידיעה מי לא בעי
מידע? re'ia belo yedia mi lo ba'ei meida? But when it comes
to seeing, then you have to know, because you have to know
נכרית בעל בת ישראל בעל בתולה בעל בעולה בעל. nochris ba'al bas
Yisrael ba'al besula ba'al be'ula ba'al. Fine. Okay, so that's what we're
saying. We are saying that we can concede that even in capital
cases, it's enough to infer, you don't need to see directly, which
is a crazy concession, we never say that. But we're saying that
the difference would be seeing without knowing. That'll help in monetary cases
but it won't help in capital cases or in a קנס knas
case. So what we haven't explained yet is how does seeing without
knowing help in monetary cases, right? I mean you always if you're
missing critical pieces of information, how's it going to help you? So
let's keep on going. יתיב רב המנונא קמיה דרב יהודה. yativ Rav
Hamnuna kamei deRav Yehuda. So Rav Hamnuna was sitting in front of
Rav Yehuda. ויתיב רב יהודה וקמיבעיא ליה. ve'yativ Rav Yehuda ve'kamiba'aya lei.
And Rav Yehuda was raising the following question. Like he asks Rav
Hamnuna, the student, like he was giving him a little בחינה. bechina.
So okay, מנה לי בידך בפני פלוני ופלוני. maneh li beyadecha bifnei
ploni u'ploni.
I say to Michael, Michael, I counted out to you a hundred
dollars in front of Jacob and David.
והעדים רואין אותו מבחוץ. veha'edim ro'in oso mibachutz. And Jacob and David,
they were peeking in from outside. Okay, so מה? ma? So what
would be the story, okay, in terms of and then you somehow
deny it and you don't know that I have witnesses because they
were on the outside so you think I don't have witnesses so
you deny it and then I bring Jacob and David into the
courtroom. So that's a perfect example of what we're really trying to
do now is explicate: what is the case by monetary matters that
seeing without knowing works, right? Because if we just said seeing without
knowing doesn't work by נפשות nefashos and it doesn't work by קנס
knas because if you don't have critical pieces of information how can
you go forward? So how does it work by a case of
דיני ממונות? dinei mamonos? Okay, so that's essentially what he was asking.
I say Michael, you owed me the money and then he denies
it, I count out money he denies it and then I trot
in witnesses who saw. So אמר ליה רב המנונא. amar lei Rav
Hamnuna. So Rav Hamnuna said back to who was this? Rav Yehuda,
excuse me, Rav Yehuda. What's Michael saying in this case?
אי אמר לא היו דברים מעולם, ei amar lo hayu devarim me'olam,
if
Michael says that you know, I never you never counted out the
money, so הוחזק כפרן. huchzak kafran. So then when I bring in
the witnesses, right, it shows that Michael is a liar, he's proven
to be a liar. Okay, now, if he's proven to be a
liar, so what? Doesn't mean he owes me the money. So Rashi
says what it means now is that if I can get him
in a situation where he has to take a שבועה shvua to
me, then he's not he wouldn't be believed to take the שבועה.
shvua. And then you and then I would or something. Right. So
that's only exactly, it's a few steps removed. אי אמר... ei amar...
אי אמר אין שקלי ודידי שקלי. i amar in shakli v'didi shakli.
Now, if Michael says, "Sure, you kept out a hundred dollars for
me, thank you very much, that was paying back the loan that
you owed me," okay, or that you were giving me a gift.
So כי אתו עדי מאי מהני? ki atu edei mai mahani? So
what good would the עדים edim do? So אמר ליה הימנו
עול. amar lei haimnu ul.
Okay,
to הימנו haimnu good, you can come into the בית מדרש. beit
midrash. Okay, you know what you, you passed the בחינה. bechina. Like
you thought it through and you realize here's the consequences. But at
the end of the day,
it means that ראיה בלא ידיעה reiyah belo yediah means nothing.
Well, it means something to make you a כפרן, kafran, but it's
not a good point about how we know therefore that the case
is שבועת העדות shvuat ha'edut because that would seem way too far
removed to be relevant for שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edut, right? Okay, אתא
ועל תא, ata ve'al ta, you enter in and come. Okay, now
so we really haven't satisfactorily explained what good this does for דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. So let's keep on going. ההוא דאמר ליה לחבריה,
hahu de'amar lei lechavreih, somebody said to his friend, מנה מניתי לך
בצד עמוד זה. maneh maniti lach betzad amud zeh.
I counted out, Michael, I counted out a hundred dollars for you
while you were standing by that tree over there, by that pillar
over there. אמר ליה לא עברתי בצד עמוד זה. amar lei lo
avarti betzad amud zeh. Michael says, "What are you talking about? I
never passed by that tree." אתו תרי סהדי ואסהידו ביה דהכי שתי
בצד עמוד זה, atu terei sahadei ve'ashidu beih dehachi shtei betzad amud
zeh, I brought two witnesses and they showed that yesterday you were,
they actually saw you, you know, urinating by that tree. אמר רב
יצחק הוחזק כפרן. amar rav Yitzchak huchzak kafran. Ah, he's proved a
liar and now he can't take an oath at least, or whatever
the way רש״י Rashi read it, he's not believed in the context
of this case. Okay, so מתקיף לה רב נחמן, matkif lah rav
Nachman, רב נחמן rav Nachman asked on this, האי דינא פרסאה הוא,
hai dina parsa'ah hu, that would be how Persians would rule such
a case. מי קאמר מעולם? mi ka'amar me'olam? When I said, "Michael,
yesterday I counted out a hundred dollars for you in this tree,"
and you said, "What are you talking about? I wasn't at that
tree," he doesn't mean that never in his life did he visit
that tree. באותו מעשה קאמר ליה. be'oto ma'aseh ka'amar lei. He means
in the context you're discussing, that never happened. It doesn't mean I
never was at that tree. Okay, so therefore forget that, that would
not be the הלכה. halacha. איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, others say, ההוא
דאמר ליה לחבריה מנה מניתי לך בצד עמוד זה אמר ליה לא
עברתי בצד עמוד זה מעולם. hahu de'amar lei lechavreih maneh maniti lach
betzad amud zeh amar lei lo avarti betzad amud zeh me'olam. I
counted out a hundred dollars, what are you talking about? I was
never at that tree. נפקו בי תרי סהדי דהכי שתי בצד עמוד
זה, nafku bei terei sahadei dehachi shtei betzad amud zeh, and there
were witnesses that he urinated by that tree. אמר רב נחמן הוחזק
כפרן. amar rav Nachman huchzak kafran. So רב נחמן rav Nachman said
that he was הוחזק כפרן. huchzak kafran. Okay, now the difference is
that he said לא עברתי בצד עמוד זה מעולם. lo avarti betzad
amud zeh me'olam. That's how this case is different. Michael didn't just
say, "What are you talking about? I wasn't at that tree." If
he just says, "I wasn't at," it means, "I wasn't at that
tree in the context you're
describing." But Michael said, "I never was at that tree. I hate
that tree. I've never been there." Okay, and then witnesses come and
say that he did urinate, that he was, you know. So is
that enough?
So אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן, amar lei Rava le'rav Nachman, to
prove that he's a liar. So אמר ליה רבא לרב נחמן כל
מילתא דלא רמיא עליה דאיניש עביד ליה ולאו אדעתיה. amar lei Rava
le'rav Nachman kol milta dela ramya aleih de'inish avid leih velav adaiteih.
Something that people aren't paying attention to, they'll do without noting. Right,
like it's completely irrelevant to somebody which tree he's urinating by. So
somebody could claim with all sincerity, "I never was at that tree,"
and then we got a videotape of the person being at that
tree, but if it was a completely irrelevant to his life when
he was there, okay, he just did not note it at all
and therefore it doesn't prove that he's a liar. I actually have,
I know somebody many years ago told me that he was, he
got a ticket for driving a U-Haul on, what would it be?
What are the highways you can't drive commercial vehicles on? On the
parkways? On Henry Hudson Parkway. For driving a commercial vehicle. So when
he went to court to defend himself, he said like, "you know,
I didn't know that a U-Haul's considered, A, there were no signs,
B, okay that's never an excuse, B, I didn't know a U-Haul's
a commercial vehicle." So the judge says, "Well, you know, it doesn't
matter, you have to know." He says, "Let me ask you something.
How many handicap," he said this to the judge, "how many handicap
stalls are there in the bathroom, you know, right by the courtroom?"
Judge says, "I don't know." He says, "You see? If it doesn't
matter to you, you don't pay attention, you don't know. If you
assume it's not relevant." Anyway, he still got the ticket.
Good for him for trying. Anyway, so things that we don't think
are relevant to our lives, we just completely are oblivious to. So
that's the מילתא דלא רמיא עליה דאיניש לאו אדעתיה. milta dela ramya
aleih de'inish lav adaiteih. Anyway, that means that we can't prove that
Michael's a liar because he totally wasn't, this
is one of the few times that רב נחמן
rav Nachman got bested in דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. Oh, there you
go. Anyway, but the question we still don't have an answer to
is, and if he was הוחזק כפרן, huchzak kafran, big deal, right?
So תוספות Tosafos makes, tries to make a scenario which also helps
explain how, how we're saying that this is a case where your
testimony really would make me win, because רש״י Rashi has it like
two stages removed. You wouldn't be able to take a שבועה, shvua,
whatever, it's still not going to make me win. So if you
take a look at תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says like
this.
Okay, ויש לומר, ve'yesh lomar, it's about six lines down in the
narrow
lines of תוספות עוסק. Tosafos ossek. He says, דהכא קאמר לא עברתי
בצד עמוד זה משמע דבעי למימר דאם עברתי. dehacha ka'amar lo avarti
betzad amud zeh mashma de'ba'ei lemeimar de'im avarti. And Michael, if he
would have said, yes you counted out it was a gift, then
obviously it wouldn't matter. But Michael says, I am telling you that
never took place and if you can prove to me that that
took place, then I will concede that I owe you the money.
Okay, and in that scenario, if I go ahead and I bring
the witnesses that I counted the money, there's a case where the
witnesses don't know what they're seeing and it'll make me win the
case. So that is at least helpful in explaining why that testimony
is ידיעה בלא ראיה. yedia belo reaya. Of course that's completely missing
from the גמרא. Gemara. But if all the witnesses prove is that
he was he urinated by that place, so that's הוחזק כפרן huchzak
kafran or whatever, that doesn't you know etc. That's the whole discussion
about was he paying attention to that or not paying attention to
that. Okay, so now let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. רב שמן
Rav Shiman אמר amar חיוב כאן וחיוב בפיקדון. chiyuv kan vechiyuv bepikadon.
So רב שמן Rav Shiman says that here's where we're going to
learn it out from פיקדון, pikadon, not based
you know not based on all of these things but based on
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. פיקדון Pikadon has broader scope and it's
limited to money, so עדות edos also is limited to money. מחכו
עליו במערבא. Machu alav bamaarava. They laughed about this in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael on this דרשה. drasha. מאי חוכא? Mai chucha?
Why is it why is it mockable? Why is it funny? דקתני
מה לפיקדון שכן לא עשה בו מושבע כנשבע dekasani mah lipikadon sheken
lo asa bo mushba kenishba because part of the קל וחומר kal
vachomer was פיקדון pikadon or the response to the קל וחומר kal
vachomer is פיקדון pikadon is not always broader. Here's the way in
which פיקדון pikadon is narrower.
פיקדון Pikadon doesn't apply when the שבועה shvua is imposed on you,
whereas by עדות edos it applies even when the שבועה shvua is
imposed. So פיקדון pikadon is sometimes narrower. שכן לא עשה בו מושבע
כנשבע sheken lo asa bo mushba kenishba מזיד כשוגג. mezid keshogeg. מכדי
מושבע מפי עצמו בעדות רב שמן מנא ליה? Michdi mushba mipi atzmo
beedos Rav Shiman minaleh? How do you know this case, like this
case says...
let's erase this...
this case says ושמעה קול אלה, veshama kol ala,
okay,
which is מושבע, mushba, somebody else made him do it. This case
says ומעלה מעל בה', umaala maal baHashem,
actually I don't think it explicitly says שבועה, shvua, it just says
מעל בה' maal baHashem means שבועה, shvua, וכחש בעמיתו, vechiches beamiso, okay,
which means that this guy is doing it, this is נשבע. nishba.
So we're saying in the response to the קל וחומר kal vachomer
that this that this case is narrower. This case is only נשבע
nishba when he took it, this case is even if מושבע, mushba,
even if it was imposed. So גמרא Gemara says one minute, how
do you know that this case is נשבע? nishba? Maybe, you know,
we said this is both מושבע mushba and נשבע. nishba. Yes, it's
a case of imposed, how do you know that this also applies
to guy taking it himself? Okay? So מושבע מפי עצמו בעדות רב
שמן מנא ליה? mushba mipi atzmo beedos Rav Shiman minaleh? What does
רב שמן Rav Shiman know the case even if the guy does
it himself? דגמר
מפיקדון, degamar mipikadon, must be he learns it out from פיקדון. pikadon.
Okay? So if he's going to learn it out from פיקדון, pikadon,
then then it'll go both ways and then this will all also
apply to מושבע. mushba. How do we get an imbalance here? How
do we get this is both and this is only one? The
only way we get both is by applying it this way. Okay?
Then we should apply it back the other way. Okay? So דגמר
מפיקדון פיקדון נמי מושבע מפי אחרים ניגמר מעדות. degamar mipikadon pikadon nami
mushba mipi acherim nigmar meedos.
So if that's true if we know עדות edos is both others
and yourself, we should say the same about פיקדון. pikadon. So גמרא
Gemara says no. ומאי חוכא? Umai chucha? Why why is that a
reason to mock it? דילמא רב שמן בקל וחומר מייתי לה? Dilma
Rav Shiman bekal vachomer mayisileh? No, רב שמן Rav Shiman can learn
out here נשבע. nishba. How do you know נשבע? nishba? It's a
קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If you're חייב chayav when somebody imposes it,
certainly you're חייב chayav when you do it yourself. Okay? So here
once you say מושבע mushba certainly נשבע. nishba. So we don't learn
these from one another. Okay? And this remains only if you do
it yourself. This is even others, so קל וחומר kal vachomer you
do it yourself. So that's not a reason to mock it, there
is that imbalance. Okay? ודילמא רב שמן בקל וחומר מייתי לה, vedilma
Rav Shiman bekal vachomer mayisileh, מפי אחרים חייב שחייב mipi acherim chayav
shechayav if other people impose it, מפי עצמו לא כל שכן? mipi
atzmo lo kol sheken? Certainly if you do it yourself? אלא חוכא
אמזיד כשוגג. Ela chucha amezid keshogeg.
Here's the here's the reason it was mocked. Because the other way
it was explained that פיקדון pikadon is it has a narrower scope
than עדות edos in the one case, the other one case it
has a narrow scope is that it only applies to עדות edos
applies even in מזיד mezid and פיקדון pikadon only in שוגג. shogeg.
דקתני. dekasani. Why is that true? And as you might remember actually
later we even said that פיקדון pikadon applies even במזיד bemezid when
we were pointing out points of comparison. מה לפיקדון שכן לא עשה
בו מושבע כנשבע מזיד כשוגג. mah lipikadon sheken lo asa bo mushba
kenishba mezid keshogeg. מכדי. Michdi. So let's take a look. מזיד גבי
עדות מנא ליה? mezid gabi edos minaleh? How do you know עדות
edos applies even in a case of מזיד? mezid? דלא כתיב ביה
ונעלם. delo kesiv beh venelam. It doesn't have that keyword ונעלם, venelam,
it was hidden. So we know it applies. הכא נמי לא כתיב
בי ונעלם. Hacha nami lo kesiv bei ve'ne'elam. Okay, but guess what?
There also it doesn't say ונעלם. ve'ne'elam. So why do you assume
that this is only שוגג? shogeg? You should assume that this is
even מזיד. meizid. So what do you mean that this is a
way in which this is a narrower scope? So אמר ליה רב
הונא ומאי חוכא, amar lei Rav Huna u'mai chucha, why is that
a reason to mock? דילמא מזיד דלאו שוגג בפיקדון ממעילה רבי שמעון
גמר לה. Dilma meizid d'laf shogeg b'pikkadon mi'me'ilah Rabbi Shimon gamar lah.
Okay, so one minute, I'll tell you why. So this, here it
doesn't say ונעלם, ve'ne'elam, no ונעלם, ve'ne'elam, so therefore even
מזיד, meizid, okay? Even. שוגג shogeg is always assumed, plus מזיד. meizid.
Okay, here it doesn't say ונעלם, ve'ne'elam, it's true, so the question
is why not therefore assume this is also מזיד? meizid? But one
minute, ומעלה מעל בה', u'ma'al ma'al b'Hashem, it compares it to מעילה,
me'ilah, and מעילה me'ilah you only bring a קרבן במעילה korban b'me'ilah
when it's בשוגג. b'shogeg. So yes, it doesn't say ונעלם, ve'ne'elam, but
there's a reason to say that ומעלה מעל ma'al ma'al means only
שוגג. shogeg. So it all makes sense. Why are you being so
bothered? What's bothering you so much, okay? Says the גמרא. Gemara. All
right, the differences are clear. Here you know נשבע nishba by a
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, here you don't have the case of מושבע,
mushba, that's one way this is a narrower scope. Here you know
מזיד meizid because it doesn't say ונעלם, ve'ne'elam, here you're going to
assume only שוגג shogeg because it's compared to מעילה. me'ilah. So that's
another way this is a narrower scope. Why do you keep on,
why do you keep on mocking? Okay, that's true. But that's an
interesting question the גמרא Gemara I guess could have asked. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like
this: Okay, where were we? So ומאי חוכא דילמא מזיד דלאו שוגג
בפיקדון ממעילה רבי שמעון גמר לה, u'mai chucha dilma meizid d'laf shogeg
b'pikkadon mi'me'ilah Rabbi Shimon gamar lah, והיינו חוכא. v'hainu chucha. Fine. Here's
the reason it was mocked. עד דגמר לה ממעילה ניגמר לה מעדות.
Ad d'gamar lah mi'me'ilah ningmar lah m'eidus. Why does he take it
for granted that we're going to learn that this is שוגג shogeg
from מעילה, me'ilah, why not learn that it's מזיד meizid because it's
and learn it out from this case? So that's already maybe a
softball question.
So why not learn that it's both?
Or שוגג shogeg and מזיד? meizid? No, מסתברא, mistavra, no, that's already
a softball question.
מסתברא ממעילה הוה ליה למילף, Mistavra mi'me'ilah havah lei l'meilaf, שכן מעילה
ממעילה. she'ken me'ilah mi'me'ilah. No, they both have the word מעילה. me'ilah.
That's a better link. אדרבה, Adarabah, מעדות הוה ליה למילף, m'eidus havah
lei l'meilaf, you should learn it out from עדות, eidus, שכן תחטא
מתחטא. she'ken techeta mi'techeta. Remember ונפש כי תחטא, ve'nefesh ki techeta, the
other דרשה drasha that learned it out? No, מסתברא ממעילה הוה ליה
למילף, mistavra mi'me'ilah havah lei l'meilaf, better to learn it out from
מעילה, me'ilah, שכן מעילה בכל נהנה בקבועה חומש ואשם. she'ken me'ilah bakol
nehneh bekavuah chomesh v'asham. So those are the various points of comparison.
What are they? So number one, they both have the word מעילה.
me'ilah.
בכל bakol means that it applies to like all people, it's not
limited to people who are כשר להעיד, kasher l'ha'id, right? It's men
and women and the whole thing. נהנה, nehneh, in this case and
in the מעילה me'ilah case, the person who is sinning is deriving
benefit. I'm withholding money from Michael, I'm swearing falsely, or I'm getting
benefit from הקדש. hekdesh. In this case, the עדות eidus who are
swearing falsely are not deriving benefit. Okay, so that's another point of
comparison. בקבועה, bekavuah, you bring a fixed cost קרבן korban as opposed
to a variable cost קרבן. korban. Okay,
and חומש ואשם chomesh v'asham and both of
them the קרבן korban for מעילה, me'ilah, that's actually quite fascinating. The
Torah, it's worth pointing out, the Torah uses the word, it refers
to a trespass against God, the word מעילה, me'ilah, the same word
used by a שבועה, shvuah,
the same word used when you benefit from הקדש, hekdesh, and the
punishment is the same when you benefit from הקדש, hekdesh, an אשם
asham and a fifth. So there's a lot of points of comparison
to מעילה. me'ilah. Okay. אדרבה Adarabah says the גמרא, Gemara, I'll say
the opposite. מעדות הוה ליה למילף, m'eidus havah lei l'meilaf, learn it
out from עדות, eidus, שכן חטא, she'ken cheit, they both say by
עדות eidus they both say, I'm sorry, here, no, here, oh, here
the comparison was that it was a חטאת. chatas. Here the comparison
is it says ונפש כי תחטא, ve'nefesh ki techeta, so it has
the same phrase, that's what the word חטא cheit means, שכן
חטא, she'ken cheit, הדיוט, hedyot, they're not talking about הקדש hekdesh issues,
they're talking about normal people. בשבועה, bishvuah, and they both take place
through an oath. ותביעה וכפירה. u'tzviya u'kfira.
This is a demand and a denial, no, not מעילה.
me'ilah. Okay, okay,
and they both take place through a demand and a denial. והן,
v'o'in, and they have all those o's that compare them. So that's
also a lot of points. So הנך נפישן, hanach nefishen, nevertheless more
points of comparison with מעילה, me'ilah, you'll count them up. Okay, so
now we're good. So what do you what are you mocking? Here
we're comparing this to מעילה, me'ilah, we'd rather compare to מעילה me'ilah
than to עדות. eidus. So here it's only שוגג shogeg and here
it's only נשבע, nishba, and this is even מזיד meizid and this
is even מושבע, mushba, so there are two ways in which this
is narrower scope than עדות. eidus. So that actually makes a lot
of sense. אלא מאי חוכא, ella mai chucha, so what's the mocking?
So כי אתא רב פפא ורב הונא בריה דרב יהושע מבי רב
אמרי היינו חוכא. ki asa Rav Pappa v'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Yehoshua
mi'bei Rav amri hainu chucha. Here's why it was mocked. מכדי, michti,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon גזירה... gzera... גמר לה גמר. gamar la gamar.
At the end he says I can't do it from a קל
וחומר, Kal Vachomer, I'll do it from a גזירה שוה. Gezeira Shava.
So למה ליה דפריך מה לקרבן שכן לא עשה בו מושבע כנשבע
מזיד כשוגג. lama leh deparich mah lekorban sheken lo asa bo mushba
k'nishba mezid keshogeg. So then why is he assuming that there are
points of difference between the two? Once at the end you're going
to have a גזירה שוה, Gezeira Shava, then we should reject all
of this. And we should say this is even במזיד b'Mezid and
this is even מפי אחרים. mipi acherim. Shouldn't that be the גזירה
שוה? Gezeira Shava? The גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava at the end should
remove, you know, destroy those distinctions? The גמרא Gemara says why is
that bothering you? ומה חוכה, u'mai chucha, why do you mock that?
דילמא כי פריך מקמי דתקבל גזירה שוה. Dilma ki parich mikamei d'tikabel
Gezeira Shava. מה? Mai? He was making those points of distinction as
I would have had these points of distinction were it not for
my גזירה שוה. Gezeira Shava. It was all a lead-in. If I
had to learn it from a קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, I couldn't,
there would have been these points of distinction and I couldn't have
learned it. So therefore I needed the גזירה שוה. Gezeira Shava. Now
that I have a גזירה שוה, Gezeira Shava, maybe those points of
distinction go away. בתר דקבל גזירה שוה לא פריך. Batar d'kabel Gezeira
Shava lo parich. Maybe it would go away. So no, is that
really true? ואמרו ליה רבא בר איסי לרבנן v'amru leh Rava bar
Isi l'rabbanan מאן תנא שבועת הפקדון לא ניתנה להתכפר man tana shvuat
hapikadon lo nitna l'hitkaper רבי שמעון
היא. Rabbi Shimon hi. No, because רבא Rava actually says that at
the end of the day, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that this
case does not apply במזיד. b'Mezid. שבועת הפקדון Shvuat haPikadon is only
בשוגג. b'Shogeg. Now if you'll remember the גמרא Gemara assumed in one
of its lists of points of comparison that it did apply במזיד.
b'Mezid. So in the end we assume because of the גזירה שוה
Gezeira Shava this does apply במזיד. b'Mezid. But רבא Rava is saying
that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon even after the גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava
says that this only applies בשוגג. b'Shogeg. And that's the question we
have. At the end when he has a גזירה שוה, Gezeira Shava,
why does he still insist on his points of distinction? Why does
he still insist that this is only בשוגג b'Shogeg and not במזיד?
b'Mezid? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
is that why they were laughing about it?
Yes. Doesn't seem like a big reason to mock something. Anyway, דילמא
dilma רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon מזיד כשוגג פריך mezid k'shogeg parich דגמר
לה ממעילה d'gamar la mi'meilah דהנהו
נפישין d'hanhu nefisheen אבל מושבע כנשבע לא פריך. aval mushba k'nishba lo
parich. The גמרא Gemara says wait, I've got an answer. So fine,
מזיד Mezid he'll hold till the very end. You know why he'll
hold till the very end? Because even after your גזירה שוה Gezeira
Shava there's still something that is actively telling us that this should
only be שוגג, Shogeg, which is the word מעילה. Meilah. So that's
why he's going to say that this will remain שוגג. Shogeg. Everybody
else disagrees, this is במזיד, b'Mezid, but he says no, מעילה Meilah
tells you שוגג. Shogeg. But you know what, after the גזירה שוה
Gezeira Shava he'll concede that this will apply even when the שבועה
shvua is imposed. The גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava will tell you that
this will apply even when the שבועה shvua is imposed.
Okay. So you know what, let's just go, let's just start the
משנה. mishna. Okay.
דתדר עדות ותגמור לה מפקדון d'tadar edut v'tigmor la mipikadon מזיד דלאו
כשוגג mezid d'lav k'shogeg מה פקדון שוגג אין מזיד לא אף עדות
שוגג אין מזיד לא. mah pikadon shogeg in mezid lo af edut
shogeg in mezid lo. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute.
Fine, so we got it in רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Even after
the גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava he'll admit it applies when it's an
imposed שבועה, shvua, but he'll insist that it's שוגג Shogeg because of
the link to מעילה. Meilah. Fine, but if you've got a גזירה
שוה, Gezeira Shava, now let's go back and say that this also
is going to be only שוגג. Shogeg. Okay?
כי היכי דיליף פקדון ממעילה. ki heichi d'yalif pikadon mi'meilah. Just the
way פקדון pikadon learned from מעילה, Meilah, now we'll apply שוגג Shogeg
and apply it here. So the גמרא Gemara says no. להכי כתב
רחמנא לעדות גבי שבועת ביטוי וגבי טומאת מקדש וקדשיו. lehachi katav Rachmana
l'edut gabei shvuat bitui v'gabei tumat mikdash v'kodshav. No. Here the absence
of ונעלם v'neelam is meaningful. Here it's true, it doesn't say ונעלם,
v'neelam, but even so we can say only שוגג Shogeg because of
the link to מעילה. Meilah. But here, you know what they say,
like you know, absence of evidence is not evidence of absence. Okay,
but sometimes, you know, sometimes absence is meaningful. If it says ונעלם
v'neelam in every single other case here and it doesn't say it
by שבועת העדות, shvuat ha'edut, it's like it's explicitly telling you that
it applies במזיד. b'Mezid. Okay, so here it just doesn't say one
way or the other, so we'll say שוגג. Shogeg. But here it's
almost explicitly telling you מזיד, Mezid, so we're not going to apply
it back. Okay. דבכולהו נאמר בהן ונעלם וכאן לא נאמר בהן ונעלם
d'b'kulhu ne'emar bahen v'neelam v'kan lo ne'emar bahen v'neelam לחייב על המזיד
כשוגג. l'chayav al ha'mezid k'shogeg. And that's why for רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon in the end this applies even by, this applies במזיד b'Mezid
because the absence of ונעלם v'neelam is like it's actively telling you
מזיד. Mezid. And but the קל וחומר, Kal Vachomer, the link tells
you this applies when it's imposed, this applies when it's imposed. We
link. Okay. But the one point of distinction רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
holds out on is this is only שוגג. Shogeg. The link doesn't
win out. מעילה Meilah tells you this is only שוגג. Shogeg. But
this remains even במזיד b'Mezid because of the absence of ונעלם. v'neelam.
What would the רבנן rabbanan say to that? Whatever, that the גזירה
שוה Gezeira Shava trumps the link to מעילה. Meilah. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara generally assumes that this is even במזיד, b'Mezid, but רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon insists no, this is only שוגג. Shogeg. That's what
the word מעילה Meilah is telling you.
All right.